My entire life I've heard this refrain
that Iran is only weeks away from
acquiring a nuclear weapon. That we have
to bomb that country preemptively to
stop them. But our own intel agencies
say Iran's nuclear program was shut down
in 2003 and isn't being restarted.
That's what they said last month. Um so
if Iran poses no real threat to the US,
why are we constantly told that it does?
Which country is Iran actually a threat
to? And if we went to war with Iran,
whose interests would that war really
serve?
Israel.
You know, it was my experience when I
was in government
that literally every single time
Benjamin Netanyahu came to the United
States, literally every single time,
he asked
whomever it was that happened to be in
the Oval Office to bomb Iran
and to do Israel's dirty work.
If
Iran is an existential threat to Israel,
okay, that's Israel's problem.
There's no reason why the United States
should bomb Iran. Now, every president,
I mean George H. W. Bush and Bill
Clinton and and George W. Bush and
Barack Obama and even uh
Donald Trump and Joe Biden
have told Netanyahu over the years to go
fly a kite.
We're not going to bomb Iran.
Uh Benjamin Netanyahu came here a couple
of weeks ago. It was on a Saturday.
Saturday visits are unusual.
But he came here because there was some
sort of crisis, some emergency. Uh there
probably wasn't. He just wanted us to
think that there was. And he comes here
and he says Israel has intelligence that
Iran is going to begin bombing Israel
imminently and we need to bomb Iran to
stop them from bombing Israel. Okay, we
don't have such intelligence. There's no
indication that that there's there's
going to be a war between Israel and
Iran. And indeed, the Iranians would get
nothing out of that. Nothing.
They don't They don't accomplish
anything by just arbitrarily attacking
Israel.
Knowing that the Israelis have as many
as 200 nuclear weapons.
What do the Iranians get out of it?
Now, on the other hand,
we used to say in the '70s
that only Nixon could go to China. And
what that meant was
the only way there was going to be peace
between the United States and China, or
even just a normalization of diplomatic
relations between the United States and
China, was if Richard Nixon, who was the
most anti-communist president in
history, the most anti-Chinese president
in history,
reached out to the Chinese and made that
peace. And that's exactly what happened.
Now, if the Democrats had done it, they
would have been accused of being soft on
communism.
They would have been called pinkos.
It They They would have been accused of
weakening the United States. But Nixon
Nixon was so anti-communist, he would be
the last person that you could accuse of
being soft on communism. He went to
China and established diplomatic
relations. Well,
I would posit that only only Trump
could go to Tehran.
Not necessarily literally,
but if anybody's going to make peace
with Iran,
wouldn't it stand to reason that it
would be the most anti-Iran person?
So, what happened? Two Saturdays ago,
Benjamin Netanyahu
um comes to the United States, emergency
visit, straight to the White House,
"Please bomb Iran." And they come out of
the meeting and Donald Trump announces
talks with the Iranians. Talks!
The Iranians for months have been
planning for some sort of an attack
either by Israel or by the United
States. But again, what does the US get
out of attacking Iran? Nothing. We get
we accomplish nothing by attacking Iran.
And so
there were talks, mostly indirect talks
in Muscat. The Iranians were in one
room, the Americans were in another
room, and the Omani foreign minister
shuttled between the two rooms. At the
end of it, there was a photo opportunity
where the two sides came together just
for a few minutes, and they spoke just
for a few minutes, but that is direct
contact.
Both sides
lauded the fact that these were serious
talks.
And they scheduled a second round of
talks in Rome that took place this past
Saturday. Now, the Omani foreign
minister also flew to Rome, shuttled
between the two rooms, and then that
shuttling was followed by direct talks.
The Iranian foreign minister made a
statement afterwards.
I think that was far more important than
what the American uh uh
special envoy uh
uh
would came out and said.
Well, yeah, thank you. Um
the Iranian foreign minister said
that the Iranian delegation had been
treated with respect.
And that
the Americans had never raised uh the
Israeli position.
So, it's not like the Israelis were
looking over our shoulder in those
negotiations. And now both sides said
that they're looking forward to the next
round of talks.
Well, you made an important point, too.
The Iranians don't have a nuclear
weapons program, despite what you've
heard from the Israelis. There have been
repeated national intelligence
intelligence estimates and special
national intel- intelligence estimates
coming out of the intelligence community
going back to 2003
in which
the conclusion of all 18 members of the
US intelligence community, not just the
CIA, all 18 members,
has been that the Iranians are not
pursuing the development of a nuclear
weapon.
They're just not. And besides, even if
they were, they don't have a delivery
system.
And so, somebody's been lying.
I think it's clear that all these years
it's been Benjamin Netanyahu.
And I think that war with Iran is not
only not imminent,
I think that for the first time in 46
years, we may actually see a
breakthrough in diplomatic relations.
There's kind of a tug-of-war, as you
mentioned, within the Trump
administration regarding Iran. There's
these people like Steve Whitcoff,
mainly,
who are making steps to engage in actual
diplomacy, talking with Iran, and trying
to solve these issues. And then, there
is another large faction of Iran hawks,
mostly Israel lobbyists, and they're
pushing for what they call the Libya
model, which is the complete dissolution
of Iranian nuclear facilities in
exchange for not being bombed by the
United States. But, isn't the Libya
model exactly why Iran would want
nuclear weapons? Gaddafi gave up his
In 2002, and I'm not 2002, 2003,
uh Steve Kappes, who was the Deputy
Director of the CIA,
um
actually, at the time he was the Deputy
He was the Associate Deputy Director for
Operations of the CIA, made a secret
trip to Libya.
And met with the Muammar uh Gaddafi.
He told Gaddafi
that um
we were going to
attack uh Iraq. This was in February
of 2003. We were going to attack Iraq
and overthrow Saddam Hussein.
And if Gaddafi didn't want to meet the
same fate, he was going to have to turn
over all of his weapons of mass
destruction.
And that's exactly what he did.
And then we overthrew him anyway.
So, you know, it's not like the rest of
the world is blind
to what the United States says versus
what the United States does. The
Iranians saw what happened in in Libya.
They saw what happened to Gaddafi
who was then lynched by his own people
at the insistence of the United States.
And so, you know, what what do you do to
protect yourself? You you develop
a an an a homegrown weapons industry.
And then you forge the closest possible
relations with Russia and China.
And that's what the Iranians have done.
Also, you know, these these Israel hawks
don't have a real appreciation
uh for
well, for several things
pertaining to Iran. One is the cohesion
of
Iranian society.
Uh you know, the Iranians are are true
believers in uniting against a single
enemy.
This notion, for example, that that we
foolishly maintained in 2002 and early
2003 that when we crossed the border
into Iraq, or the Iraqi people would
throw flowers on us. It was so
nonsensical
as to be funny. But but people inside
the administration believed it.
Well, to believe today that as soon as
we cross the border, as soon as we start
bombing Iran, the Iranians are going to
throw flowers at us and and get on their
knees to thank us for liberating them
from from their theocratic overlords,
that's just simply not true.
It's just not.
They're going to unite against an
invading army.
And they're going to fight us like the
Iranians did.
I mean, like the Iraqis did, rather.
They're going to fight us like the the
Afghans did. They're going to fight us
like the Vietnamese did.
There's going not going to be any thanks
for for the liberation
because there's no liberation.
Uh in the meantime,
Iran is is huge.
It's It's This isn't Afghanistan we're
talking about or even Iraq. It's a
gigantic country with with a lot of
people.
And we haven't taken that into
consideration. And finally, we really
don't know
what the response would be to an
American attack on Iran from the
Russians and the Chinese.
I for one don't think that they'll just
sit by and uh and let it happen without
there being some sort of a response. And
that response could be catastrophic.
National Security Advisor Mike Waltz is
a leading figure in Trump's cabinet
pushing for this war with Iran.
Drop Site News today revealed that his
new director for Israel and Iran is
Mairav Kahana from the hawkish
Foundation for Defense of Democracies,
but who more importantly was previously
an employee at the Israeli Ministry of
Defense. John, how
like that get a security clearance? That
seems highly unusual.
It's It's highly unusual.
Um and you know, it's not It's not
unique to Donald Trump, although it's
inexcusable. It's inexcusable no matter
who the president is.
But uh
but Bill Clinton did the same thing.
Uh where he named a he named
a dual US-Israeli citizen
to be ambassador to Israel, for heaven's
sake.
Um
I I honestly don't know how something
like this happens unless either the FBI
is ignored or the FBI is told to ignore
the fact that this person may have dual
loyalties.
I think it's very, very dangerous
because the Israelis are rated for rated
as critical threat for
counterintelligence in the US
intelligence community. They're They're
rated at the same level
as the Russians, the Chinese, the
Iranians, the North Koreans, and the
Cubans.
And so, I wouldn't want anybody with
ties to Israel anywhere near the
National Security Council, let alone to
be one of the deputy directors of the
National Security Council.
I don't know how this happens. I don't
know why this person isn't already
being, you know, investigated for
for um
espionage, or for some sort of violation
of the Espionage Act.
But, um this is the situation we find
ourselves in. And I think people get
away with it because there's no public
outrage.
To me, this is huge news. I saw this at
DropSite as well.
Where I didn't see it was in the New
York Times, the Washington Post, the
Wall Street Journal.
And that's, I think, part of the
problem.
I want to ask you about another country
that we're at war with right now, which
is Somalia. We've been at war in Somalia
for over two decades, yet most Americans
know next to nothing about it. The New
York Times recently reported that some
in the State Department wanted to pull
out of Mogadishu, but hawks like
Sebastian Gorka are pushing to send more
troops, escalate strikes, and install a
friendly regime. The Atlantic Council
says that withdrawal is too risky. But,
haven't we heard this argument before?
That if we just try a little harder, use
more force, train more troops, peace
will follow? Doesn't this feel like the
same failed playbook we've seen over and
over again with the surge, for instance,
or Ukraine's counteroffensive, or with
the war in Afghanistan?
Oh, yeah. We did it throughout the
Vietnam War. We did it in Afghanistan.
We did it in Iraq, and it always, always
fails.
I I've been to Somalia. It's a failed
state. There is no government in
Somalia. Somalia would be relatively
easily broken up because because uh
two of the northern provinces,
Somaliland and Puntland,
want to uh be independent countries.
Somaliland has declared independence.
Nobody's recognized it yet. They've
begged us to recognize it and we
haven't. Uh
but you know, you see here's another
example where you've got the likes of
Sebastian Gorka in charge of of of a
policy like this. Sebastian Gorka
is one of the Deputy National Security
Advisors. And this is a guy who only
lasted for 30 days in the first Trump
administration because he couldn't get a
security clearance.
And the reason he couldn't get a
security clearance is that he wears his
father's Nazi Party lapel pin.
Okay, not neo-Nazi, the actual Nazi
Party
that was in charge of Hungary during the
Second World War. He wears his father's
Nazi Party lapel pin.
Um he's an
unabashed
supporter
of Nazi ideology.
And this is the guy that we've put in
charge.
So, you know, this is something I
that I've never understood about about
Donald Trump. On the one hand, he talks
about
um he talks about pulling out or ending
pulling out of or ending
these these endless wars, right? These
endless troop commitments. And then on
the other hand, he surrounds himself
with the likes of John Bolton
and Mike Pompeo and Gina Haspel and
other swamp creatures and lovers of
foreign interventions that he's been
railing against.
So, it's like, buddy, pick an ideology
and stick with it.
You can't say you're anti-war and then
surround yourself with pro-war people
like Marco Rubio, for example.
You know why Marco Rubio is not carrying
out these talks with the Iranians and
Steve Witcoff is is because Rubio is one
of the ones that wants to bomb Iran.
So, I I just don't understand it. You
know, if I were president,
somebody having been a part of the
Atlantic Council would be disqualifying
for federal service.
It wouldn't be, you know, a talent base
that I would go to to staff my National
Security Council. It would be
disqualifying.
But, Donald Trump just seems to not
really stand for anything
other than Donald Trump.
I want to ask you now about the
US-backed Israeli genocide of Gaza.
Amazingly, there are still plenty of
defenders, and I've seen a number of
self-declared terrorism experts like Max
Abrams or Douglas Murray explain why the
war is not only justified, but an
effective approach to counterterrorism.
And it comes from this theory that if
you follow a sledgehammer approach, if
you drop enough bombs, that you're going
to deter your enemies from attacking
you.
And you don't have to resolve any
political problems or resolve any
grievances that caused the terrorism in
the first place. You just bomb everyone,
and that's how you discourage terrorism.
And actually, I don't think you have to
be an expert at all in terrorism or
counterterrorism uh to figure this out.
I think it's pretty intuitive that if
you bomb people and kill their families,
they're going to hate you and want
revenge. The first suicide bombers in
Iraq, for instance, were Palestinians
who suffered under Israeli repression
and occupation. The 1993 World Trade
Center bombing perpetrator, Ramzi
Yousef, said that he was motivated to,
quote, "Stop the killings of Arabs by
Israeli troops." Bin Laden said
similarly about his motivation for 9/11
in his letter to America, which was a
document that was purged from the
Guardian website last year and censored
all over social media once people my age
started to notice these connections
between US support for Israel and
terrorism. So, we've been told we have
to bomb the Middle East and support
Israel to stop terrorism, but is there
anything that generates more terrorism
than bombing the Middle East and
supporting Israel?
No. And you know what? I thought that
was clear a generation ago.
When when I was in Pakistan with the
CIA, I was the uh
I was the uh
chief of counterterrorism operations
there.
And to a man, every single one of the of
the ground-level Al-Qaeda fighters that
we captured told exactly the same story.
The bottom line being they had no real
beef with the United States. They
couldn't even find the United States on
a map. The beef was with US foreign
policy and support of Israel.
The the beef really at the at the end of
the day was was Israel.
And many of them said that they didn't
really care one way or the other about
the United States until they saw news
coverage
of Israeli soldiers with their boots on
the necks of Palestinian women.
Right? Or news footage of dead
Palestinian children thanks to Israeli
attacks.
And so it's that kind of behavior
that creates terrorism, that motivates
terrorists, that leads to more
terrorism, not less terrorism.
If you want less terrorism,
respect civil rights and civil
liberties, and implement economic
development and education. It's as
simple as that. But it takes time and it
takes money.
This notion of the of the sledgehammer
being used as policy, it has never
worked. Never. Besides being illegal.
Right? It's it's a violation of of uh
international law. It's a war crime, a
crime against humanity to target
civilian populations. And that's exactly
what the Israelis have have doing. The
Israelis don't even dispute, for
example,
the numbers of civilian casualties, and
those numbers are coming from Hamas's
Ministry of Health.
And the Israelis say, "Yeah, yeah, we we
have killed that many people. Yeah,
they're almost all civilians."
And so, why isn't the world doing
something about it?
But, you're right, this is just a recipe
for failure. And when I say failure, I
mean, at the end of the day, the
Israelis are going to drag the United
States down with them.
And it's just going to lead to more
attacks and more violence and more death
all over the world.